Yura Malitsky

Curriculum Vitae

Faculty of Mathematics
University of Vienna
Oskar-Morgenstern-Platz 1
1090 Vienna, Austria
☑ yurii.malitskyi@univie.ac.at
﴿ ymalitsky.com

- T	1		•		
	S	03/10	OMI	010	00
- 10	"	PXI.	, רו	$e_{\rm II}$	
		exp	CII	CI	

-
Assistant professor in Computational Optimization , <i>University of Vienna</i> , Faculty of Mathematics
Assistant professor, Linköping University, Department of Mathematics
Postdoc researcher , <i>EPFL</i> , Laboratory for Information and Inference Systems, Group of Prof. Volkan Cevher
Postdoc researcher , <i>University of Göttingen</i> , Institute for Numerical and Applied Mathematics, Group of Prof. Russell D. Luke
Postdoc researcher , <i>Graz University of Technology</i> , Institute for Computer Graphics and Vision, Group of Prof. Thomas Pock

Education

2012–2015	PhD student, Taras Shevchenko University of Kyiv, Faculty of Cybernetics, Applied
	Mathematics

- 2010–2012 **MSc**, *Taras Shevchenko University of Kyiv*, Faculty of Cybernetics, Applied Mathematics
- 2006–2010 **BSc**, Taras Shevchenko University of Kyiv, Faculty of Cybernetics, Applied Mathematics

PhD thesis

title Efficient projection methods for variational inequalities and composite optimization problems.

supervisor Prof. Volodymyr V. Semenov

description The dissertation was dedicated to the development of new algorithms for monotone variational inequalities and composite minimization problems.

Fields of interests

- Mathematical optimization
 Nonlinear analysis
- Machine learningAlgorithms

Awards

2015 SIAM Student Paper Award for "Projected reflected gradient method for monotone variational inequalities" (SIAM J. Optimization 25, 2015)

Scholarships and grants

- 2022 Knut and Alice Wallenberg Foundation Prize, co-PI. Together with Erik G. Larsson (PI), Carlo Fischione (co-PI), and Mikael Johansson (co-PI). Total: SEK 30 mln
- 2020-2023 Wallenberg AI, Autonomous Systems and Software Program Faculty
- 2006-2015 Ukrainian government scholarship
- 2010-2011 Victor Pinchuk Foundation Fellow

— Publication

- [1] A. Alacaoglu, A. Böhm, and Y. Malitsky. Beyond the golden ratio for variational inequality algorithms. *J. Mach. Learn. Res.*, 24:1–33, 2023. arXiv: 2212.13955. URL: http://jmlr.org/papers/v24/22-1488.html.
- [2] Z. Chen, E. G. Larsson, C. Fischione, M. Johansson, and Y. Malitsky. Over-the-air computation for distributed systems: something old and something new. *IEEE Network*, 2023. DOI: 10.1109/MNET. 126.2200205. arXiv: 2211.00767.
- [3] Z. Chen and Y. Malitsky. Over-the-air computation with multiple receivers: a space-time approach. *IEEE Wireless Communications Letters*, 12(8):1399–1403, 2023. DOI: 10.1109/LWC.2023.3275760.
- [4] Y. Malitsky and K. Mishchenko. Adaptive proximal gradient method for convex optimization. 2023. arXiv: 2308.02261.
- [5] Y. Malitsky and M. K. Tam. A first-order algorithm for decentralised min-max problems. 2023. arXiv: 2308.11876.
- [6] Y. Malitsky and M. K. Tam. Resolvent splitting for sums of monotone operators with minimal lifting. *Math. Program.*, 201(1):231–262, 2023. DOI: 10.1007/s10107-022-01906-4. arXiv: 2108.
- [7] A. Alacaoglu and Y. Malitsky. Stochastic variance reduction for variational inequality methods. In *Proceedings of Thirty Fifth Conference on Learning Theory*, volume 178, pages 778–816. PMLR, 2022. arXiv: 2102.08352. URL: https://proceedings.mlr.press/v178/alacaoglu22a.html.
- [8] F. J. Aragón-Artacho, Y. Malitsky, M. K. Tam, and D. Torregrosa-Belén. Distributed forward-backward methods for ring networks. *Computational optimization and applications*, 2022. DOI: 10.1007/s10589-022-00400-z. arXiv: 2112.00274.
- [9] A. Alacaoglu, Y. Malitsky, and V. Cevher. Convergence of adaptive algorithms for weakly convex constrained optimization. In *NeurIPS*, volume 34, pages 14214–14225, 2021. arXiv: 2006.06650. URL: https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2021/hash/76c073d8a82d9ddaf993300be03ac70f-Abstract.html.
- [10] A. Alacaoglu, Y. Malitsky, and V. Cevher. Forward-reflected-backward method with variance reduction. *Computational optimization and applications*, 80(2):321–346, 2021. DOI: 10.1007/s10589-021-00305-3.
- [11] M.-L. Vladarean, Y. Malitsky, and V. Cevher. A first-order primal-dual method with adaptivity to local smoothness. In *NeurIPS*, volume 34, pages 6171–6182, 2021. arXiv: 2110.15148. URL: https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2021/hash/310b60949d2b6096903d7e8a539b20f5-Abstract.html.
- [12] A. Alacaoglu, Y. Malitsky, P. Mertikopoulos, and V. Cevher. A new regret analysis for adam-type algorithms. In *Proceedings of the 37th International Conference on Machine Learning*, volume 119, pages 202–210. PMLR, 2020. arXiv: 2003.09729. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v119/alacaoglu20b.html.
- [13] Y. Malitsky. Golden ratio algorithms for variational inequalities. *Mathematical Programming*, 184:383–410, 2020. DOI: 10.1007/s10107-019-01416-w. arXiv: 1803.08832.
- [14] Y. Malitsky and K. Mishchenko. Adaptive gradient descent without descent. In *Proceedings of the 37th International Conference on Machine Learning*, volume 119, pages 6702–6712. PMLR, 2020. arXiv: 1910.09529. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v119/malitsky20a.html.
- [15] Y. Malitsky and M. K. Tam. A forward-backward splitting method for monotone inclusions without cocoercivity. *SIAM Journal on Optimization*, 30(2):1451–1472, 2020. DOI: 10.1137/18M1207260. arXiv: 1808.04162.
- [16] K. Mishchenko, D. Kovalev, E. Shulgin, P. Richtárik, and Y. Malitsky. Revisiting stochastic extragradient. In *International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics*, 2020. arXiv: 1905. 11373. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v108/mishchenko20a.html.
- [17] E. R. Csetnek, Y. Malitsky, and M. K. Tam. Shadow Douglas-Rachford splitting for monotone inclusions. *Applied Mathematics & Optimization*, 80(3):665–678, 2019. DOI: 10.1007/s00245-019-09597-8. arXiv: 1903.03393.

- [18] Y. Malitsky and P. Ochs. Model function based conditional gradient method with Armijo-like line search. In *Proceedings of the 36th International Conference on Machine Learning*, pages 4891–4900, 2019. arXiv: 1901.08087. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v97/ochs19a/ochs19a.pdf.
- [19] D. R. Luke and Y. Malitsky. Block-coordinate primal-dual method for nonsmooth minimization over linear constraints. In *Large-Scale and Distributed Optimization*, pages 121–147. Springer, Cham, 2018. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-97478-1_6. arXiv: 1801.04782.
- [20] Y. Malitsky. Proximal extrapolated gradient methods for variational inequalities. *Optimization Methods and Software*, 33(1):140–164, 2018. DOI: 10.1080/10556788.2017.1300899. arXiv: 1601.04001.
- [21] Y. Malitsky and T. Pock. A first-order primal-dual algorithm with linesearch. *SIAM Journal on Optimization*, 28(1):411–432, 2018. DOI: 10.1137/16M1092015. arXiv: 1608.08883.
- [22] Y. Malitsky. The primal-dual hybrid gradient method reduces to a primal method for linearly constrained optimization problems. 2017. arXiv: 1706.02602.
- [23] Y. Malitsky. Projected reflected gradient methods for monotone variational inequalities. *SIAM Journal on Optimization*, 25(1):502–520, 2015. DOI: 10.1137/14097238X. arXiv: 1502.04968.
- [24] Y. V. Malitsky and V. Semenov. A hybrid method without extrapolation step for solving variational inequality problems. *Journal of Global Optimization*, 61(1):193–202, 2015. DOI: 10.1007/s10898-014-0150-x. arXiv: 1501.07298.
- [25] Y. V. Malitsky and V. Semenov. An extragradient algorithm for monotone variational inequalities. *Cybernetics and Systems Analysis*, 50(2):271–277, 2014. DOI: 10.1007/s10559-014-9614-8.

Conferences and Workshops

- Graz, September Abstract "Distributive algorithms for saddle point problems", ÖMG Tagung 2023
- Paris, June 2023 Abstract "Adaptive first-order methods in convex optimization", Foundations of Computational Mathematics
- Seattle, June 2023 Abstract "Adaptive proximal gradient method", SIAM conference on Optimization
- Stockholm, June, Abstract "Adaptive gradient descent without descent", Mathematics of Complex Data 2022

Online, NeurIPS

December, 2021

- Online, October, Abstract "A Forward-Backward Splitting Method for Monotone Inclusions Without Coco-2021 ercivity", 2021 INFORMS Annual Meeting
- Online, July, 2020 ICML
- Vienna, February, Abstract "Adaptive gradient descent without descent", Workshop of the Research Group 2020 on "Applied Mathematics with Emphasis on Optimization
 - Cluj-Napoca Abstract "Golden ratio algorithm for variational inequalities", Games, Dynamics, April, 2019 Optimization–2019
 - Vienna, Abstract "On a new method for monotone inclusions", ESI workshop: Numerical February, 2019 Algorithms in Nonsmooth Optimization
 - Vienna, Abstract: "Bilevel composite minimization problems", Vienna Workshop on Computa-December, 2018 tional Optimization
- Marburg, Abstract: "Primal-dual algorithm for linearly constrained optimization problem", 4th November, 2018 Central European Set-Valued and Variational Analysis Meeting
 - Bordeaux, Abstract: "Primal-dual algorithm for linearly constrained optimization problem", 23rd
 - July, 2018 International Symposium on Mathematical Programming
 - Malta, Abstract: "Primal-dual algorithm for linearly constrained optimization problem", 9th
 - May, 2018 International Conference on Inverse Problems: Modeling and Simulation

- Chemnitz, Abstract: "Golden ratio algorithms for variational inequalities", 3rd Central European November, 2017 Set-Valued and Variational Analysis Meeting
- Oaxaca, Mexico, Abstract: "Golden ratio algorithms for variational inequalities", Splitting Algorithms,
- September, 2017 Modern Operator Theory, and Applications
 - Vancouver, Abstract: "Novel methods for saddle point problems", SIAM Conference on Optimiza-May, 2017 tion
 - Münster, Abstract: "A first-order primal-dual algorithm with linesearch", with T. Pock, Workshop: February, 2017 Shape, Images and Optimization.
- Graz, Abstract: "A first-order primal-dual algorithm with linesearch", with T. Pock, SFB
- September, 2016 Workshop: Imaging with Modulated/Incomplete Data 2016
 - Tokyo, Abstract: "New Projection Methods for Monotone Variational Inequalities", The Fifth August, 2016 International Conference on Continuous Optimization (ICCOPT-2016).
 - Poznan, Abstract: "Proximal extrapolated gradient methods for variational inequalities", 28th July, 2016 European Conference on Operational Research.
 - Kyiv, Abstract: "A Douglas-Rachford method for best approximation pair for two disjoint October, 2014 intersections of closed convex sets", VI International Conference 'Computational and Applied Mathematics' dedicated to Ivan Lyashko.
- Heidelberg, 1 Heidelberg Laureate Forum. September, 2013
- Kyiv, Abstract: "A Variant of Tseng's Splitting Method for Monotone Inclusion Problem", V September, 2013 International Conference 'Computational and Applied Mathematics'
- Kyiv, Abstract: "The approximation of a common fixed point of a finite number of Fejér map-September, 2012 pings in Hilbert space", V International Conference 'Computational and Applied Mathematics'

Referee service

- Mathematical Programming
- SIAM J. Optimization
- Mathematical Methods of Operations Research
- Computational Optimization and Application
- Journal on Optimization Theory and Application
- o Journal of Mathematical Imaging and Vision
- o Journal of Global Optimization
- Journal of Scientific Computing
- Set-Valued and Variational Analysis

- Operations Research Letters
- Numerical Algorithms
- Inverse Problems
- Optimization
- Optimization Letters
- NeurIPS
- o ICML
- ICLR
- COLT

Teaching experience

- 2022 Master course: Mathematical Optimization
- 2022 WASP PhD course: WASP Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning
- 2022 WASP PhD course: Mathematics for Machine Learning
- 2022 PhD course: Nonlinear Optimization
- 2021 Vienna Graduate School on Computational Optimization: "Continuous Optimization: between Mathematics and Computation"
- 2018-2019 Numerical methods I Teaching assistant
- 2014-2015 Analysis I Teaching assistant
- 2013-2014 Analysis II Teaching assistant

2013-2014 Functional analysis — Teaching assistant
 2006-2014 Olympiad mathematics for high school students